Hello and welcome back to lamrim.
We are starting the ninth lesson.
I like to call it
"Journey to the Center of the Sun."
We've already talked about how
there is something big and powerful enough -
like a nuclear bomb - that can be used to clean
ketchup off your shirt.
And I'm not exaggerating.
I want you to think so.
Imagine,
today is Independence Day in America.
I am performing on Independence Day.
We often go on a picnic with our family.
It's the middle of summer,
and American kids will be eating hot dogs
or hamburgers, and they'll use too much ketchup,
and some of the ketchup will end up in here.
Imagine that in order to clean this, Mom sends a shirt or blouse into the heart of the sun,
[inaudible]
to clean a little stain of ketchup, red ketchup.
I know it sounds strange,
but I'd like you to try to think about it.
I would like you to try to think about this.
I don't know what they are compared to.
Yes, I don't know.
Just put some tiny thing in the middle of the sun, okay?
So today we are going to visit the center of the sun.
And I am happy to report that we have just reached the third and final section of lamrim.
Steps on the path to enlightenment.
Right now we are going to move on
to the actions of a bodhisattva.
We are about to move on to the
thinking and activity of a bodhisattva,
who is a person of the highest faculties.
KYES BU CHEN PO (kyes bu chien po)
What does it mean a person of great abilities.
Those of you, especially those who have been following this lamrim for the last ten years,
you should be very happy that you survived
and that I survived to get to the last part.
We have come to the last part.
This is the last third.
So, these mathematicians among you must be thinking: okay, Geshe-la,
you just said that we have 25% left.
So why is it the last third?
And the answer is that
Pabongkha Rinpoche's address in the last two days of
lamrim is too short.
His presentation of meditation
and his presentation of the vision of emptiness, the
last two perfections of the six, are
not too long.
And I don't know what happened.
I mean, sometimes it's
like the sponsor came to him and said we're going to run out of food in two days.  Wrap it up
!
It's possible -
maybe this is a mystical message from Tara.
Maybe, I don’t know,
maybe he had another appointment in another city.
But if you ask me, Pabongka Rinpoche
made the last two parts shorter because
Je Tsongkhapa revealed them in his great lamrim.  The
Great Book
of Steps to Enlightenment,
Lam Rim Chenmo
Tsongkapa has done such a great job that I think
I just see Pabongka Rinpoche saying,
you know, guys,
I don't have much reason to teach this part
because Tsongkapa has already taught it
and he has done it in an extraordinary way.
There are many, many stories about how
Tsongkhapa wrote these last two parts,
and I am very happy
that we will study them together.
So we are going to finish this lamrim series
with some amazing teachings on meditation and emptiness.
Why is this part about the steps of the path for people who have bodhicitta,
for Bodhisattvas,
not as long as it could be.
So, let's go.
Let's read Tibetan.
sum pa kye pu chen pyo lam kyi rim (GSUM PA SKYES BU CHEN PO'I LAM GYI RIM)
par lo chang wa la (PAR BLO SBYANG BA LA)
Let us train our hearts in the steps of the path
for people of great ability.
People who are bodhisattvas.
thek chhen kyi juk go sem kye kho nar ten pa phen yon tang che pa (THEG CHEN GYI 'JUG SGO SEMS BSKYED KHO NAR BSTAN PA PHAN YON DANG BCAS PA)
He says that we are going to reveal the
bodhisattva way of life,
we are going to cover it in three different stages.
Number one.
thek chhen kyi juk go (THEG CHEN GYI 'JUG SGO)
If you want to enter the path of the Bodhisattva,
there is only one way to get there.
By achieving a certain state of mind.
If you want to achieve enlightenment,
if you want to have a chance to become enlightened,
if you want to have a chance to help the world,
there is only one way.
You must obtain bodhicitta.
You must have this desire to achieve enlightenment
so that you can help countless beings.
Now I want to talk about the infinite.
Bodhicitta is directed towards countless sentient beings.
It is not aimed at all the people in your city, or all the people in your country, or all the people on this planet.
Run --
if we want to send a virus to the middle of the sun,
if we want to visit the center of the sun,
run from this idea that we are working
for all the people on this planet.
We don't do that.
Get rid of this idea that we're trying to help
all the fish and all the birds and all the animals
that walk on land.
We don't do that.  That's
not the point.
We cover the entire Universe.
We decide today that I would like to help
every living being in the Universe.
Every little virus.
Bacterium.
Every whale.
Every person in the Universe.  If
you're going out at night in Sedona or beyond,
Rim Rock is the place to be.
And look at the stars and just try to imagine.
So, first of all, you cannot practice the bodhisattva way of life
unless you develop your mind to this, to this goal.
And if you really experience this,
which takes some practice,
if you really send your mind --
if you are really able to get bodhichitta,
then what you still have to do in this world is nothing.
Nothing more.  It's not important.
To help all the people in this world, it's a small thing.
It's very simple.
phen yon tang che pa (PHAN YON DANG BCAS PA) means
I want to tell you about the benefits of this kind of thinking.
This is the first step.
chang chup tu sem kye pe tshyul (BYANG CHUB TU SEMS BSKYED PA'I TSUL)
Second step.
How will you get to this breakthrough?
Mental breakthrough?
How to perceive the entire Universe
and all the beings in it?
And then develop love for them.  Is
this even possible?  Is
this even possible?
This is already the second step.
Step three.
We are going to learn how to act like a bodhisattva.
Once you have this hope of becoming a bodhisattva, then
what should I do?
How should I spend the hours of my day
if I want to act like a bodhisattva?
What should I do?
What will my schedule be?
Fine.  Here is the first of them.
tang po ni (DANG PO NI,)
te tar kye wu chung dring ki kap su ngge jyung ki sam pe kun ne lang (DE LTAR SKYES BU CHUNG 'BRING GI SKABS SU NGES 'BYUNG GI BSAM PAS KUN NAS BSLANGS)
So now that we have gone through the steps of the path for people of lower ability and average ability,
at least, you must have this feeling that
in reality this life is pain, in reality this life is a disaster.
The virus just makes it obvious.
But it has always been like this.  There
has always been a virus called Death.
This is a new virus.  It is much smaller.
But now we all at least think about it.
хлак пе лап па сум ла бе пе (LHAG PA'I BSLAB PA GSUM LA 'BAD PAS)
Then we would have to
work on three extraordinary workouts.
Treat other people well.
Spend time in meditation.
And then try to see
that things do not happen from their own side.
You can achieve nirvana on your own, and you can get out of the Wheel of Life.
If you practice this worldview, you can, it is possible.
We have already taught you, we are finished with it.
But I don't want you to stop there. I don't want you to stop there.
I want you -- there
are more important things to do. There are much more important things to do. Don't stop there.
pang cha tham che ma pang (SPANG BYA THAMS CAD MA SPANGS)
If  you're just going to stick to what I've taught you so far,
you're not going to cleanse your heart
of all the impure things in it.
thob cha yon ten (thob bya yon tan)
tham che kyang yong su ma dzok pe (thams cad kyang yong su ma dzok pe (ma dzok pe (ma rdzog pe (ma rdzog pe (rang ton tang (rang
don tang,)
shen ton yang nyi tshe wa le mi jyung gzhan don yang nyi tse ba la mi 'byung) nyi tshe wa
(nyi tse ba) is a very discouraging word here.
This is a very sad word.  It
says here that you can work on the paths that I have taught you so far,
you can continue to work
on all the meditations that I have already taught you,
but the amount of good
that you will do for yourself and others
is only a small part of what you need to do.
ньи цхе ва (NYI TSE BA) means only a small amount of what
you have to do.
And by the way, the most common use of this word is the word meaning hell on earth.
And this is very strange.
That is, there is a big hell that people can end up in.
But I always think about the person who was in a car accident and the car exploded and they were engulfed in flames.
In the scriptures it is called
NYI TSI BA'I DMYAL BA.
A little piece of hell in this airplane.  In this plane of reality.
And so this word NYI TSI BA means just a tiny piece.
And here he says: do you want to help yourself
and do you want to help other people?
Everything I have taught you so far for 10 years is
NYI TSI BA.
This is just a small part of what you could do, and now we are ready to get down to the serious stuff.
Well Geshe-la, why did we spend 10 years to make NYI TSI BA, this little thing?
Why don't we just move on to higher things?
Because this little thing is a ladder
that will help you reach higher things.
You cannot achieve higher things
unless you do the other two parts.
Unless you practice all the steps of lam-rim
in the correct order,
you will never get to the bodhisattva part.
So you can't just say you don't want it.
Part of the bodhisattva way of life is mastery of the lower path, which is what helped you get here.
And you never reject them.
You just grow out of them.
The idea of ​​Buddhism is
that once you are ready,
and once you are prepared,
you should immediately go straight into the
bodhisattva way of life,
because if you don't --
you will still have to do it again,
and sooner or later you will have to come here.
Maybe it will take a lifetime.
Maybe it will happen later in this life.
Every now and then people come to me and say, I'm going to take a break from this Dharma.
I feel like I need to take a break.
I have other things to do right now.
I'm working on a big project
or I have family things to do,
and I need to take a break.
When I was in India, I told one of my teachers once, I remember
45 years ago.
And I said, "I need to take a break," and they looked  at me and said, "Yeah, okay, but you'll come back."
You'll come back because there's nowhere else to go.
You'll come back. You'll come back to it because you need to come back to it. Life will bring you here again.
Because that's life. You need lamrim.
Life will always bring you back to lamrim.
Until you die.
And it will still bring you back to it later. @SLAR
means you have to come back again.
SLAR THEG CHEN LA GZHI NAS
shi ne (GZHI NAS) means you'll lose a lot of time
if you need to come back to it.
You might as well do it right now
instead of coming back to it later.
Next image.
A little bit of this
I want to do with you in this class, class 9.
I call it "Journey to the Center of the Sun."
So, in this image...
I tried to find a picture that was close
to  explanation of what it means to attain bodhichitta.
So this picture looks a little...
we think, Seiji, Tim, and I,
we think there's a little bit of a New Age feel to it. It
looks like it was painted in Sedona, Arizona.
It has a little bit of a New Age feel to it, but let me tell you something.
If you ever attain bodhichitta,
it feels...
This picture is very close. This picture is close enough. Can you leave it? Just for a minute? There
's no crazy stuff in this picture,
and it's not some hippie thing.
When you attain bodhichitta, real bodhichitta,
it feels like this.
So maybe you want to copy this picture.
We've already paid for it.
So you can use it at home. You can leave it at home.
You could keep this picture.
Maybe put it on your phone wallpaper.
It's pretty close to the feeling of bodhichitta.
So I'd like to take you on a little journey, just  Let's just have some fun, maybe for five minutes.
Let's explore what it feels like to
have real bodhichitta for the first time.
So we're not talking about approximate,
what do you call it? Partial bodhichitta.
Or trying to feel like we have bodhichitta.
Let's talk about the real thing.
The day you see emptiness directly
and have a direct experience of bodhichitta,
let's just live it, because that's such a blessing.
And that's the atomic bomb.
If you keep working on that, if you keep working on that,
feeling what it's like, if you keep listening to that part,
it will help destroy the virus.
I believe it will help destroy the virus.
It's like a nuclear weapon.
And the virus is like a ketchup stain.
So there you go.
Let's just try to imagine for five minutes
what it feels like to achieve bodhichitta.
There you go.
Let's take ten slow breaths.
Focus on the exhalations, long exhalations, don't worry.  about inhaling, your body will inhale on its own.
Please imagine
that you have just seen emptiness directly.
And you come out of this direct perception,
and you return to what we call ordinary meditation, which is still not in the world.
You are in a state of deep meditation,
you are still sitting on your pillow.
Your eyes are closed.
Then suddenly an image of your mother appears before your mind
. This is your mother. The
perfect image of your mother. A living image.
This is really your mother.
Maybe how you remember her best.
She still looks like this.
She is looking at you.
She is looking into your eyes.
Even though she seems to be in the front of your consciousness, she is looking into your eyes.
With great love and a sense of need.
She really needs help.
In some sense, she is in trouble.
As if she is jumping from the Titanic or something,
and she is looking at you with such eyes.
She is saying I need you, I need help.
And then you say to her out loud in your heart:
“Don’t worry, Mom, I’ll take care of you.”
And I’ll be strong enough to take care of you.
You don’t have to worry.
I’ll have enough strength to help you
and I will, I promise.
And then her image kind of dissolves in your mind, and suddenly your father’s image appears.
And you look at your father.
And he has the same look.
It’s a kind of expectation. But also fear.
So he looks at you like,
“Can you help me?”
Life is getting hard, life is hard right now.
Then you say, “Dad, don’t worry. I’m doing it!
I’m studying lam-rim.
I’m studying a lot about emptiness.
And actually, I know that I’ll have the tools
to help you soon.
So don’t worry. I’m doing it.
I’ll take care of it.”
And please don’t—
you don’t have to be afraid. You don’t have to worry.
I know what to do, and I’m doing it.
Everything will be okay, so don’t worry!
And then maybe someone  someone else close to you in your life,
your wife or your husband or your children,
one of your children,
their image appears before your mind.
Just their faces.
And they also look at you like, “Can you help me? Things are bad, really bad!”
Things are mortally dangerous, there is no other hope. Can you help me
?
And you say:
I have everything under control, I will take care of it.
I can.
I will be strong enough to take care of you.
You really have nothing to worry about.
I know what is going on.
I know your situation.
I know what this life is like.
I have it all figured out
and I will take care of you completely.
You have nothing to worry about.
You really have nothing to worry about.
I will take care of it.
And then that face disappears, and then you can start going through the faces of people you know.
Close people, close relatives.
Uncles, aunts.
Brothers, sisters.
Nephews, nieces.
One by one they pop up in front of you
and you reassure them.
And you  say, “It’s true, I’ll take care of it.
You won’t have to worry about anything.”
And so we go through all the people you know.
All the people you’ve ever met in your life.
Then you start working with all the people you haven’t met yet, and all the people that exist in this world.
Start with your own environment.
Go to a city, the whole city, and you know you can’t reach everyone.
But take a person here and take a person there.
Take within the continent you live on.
Reach everyone.
And then move on.
To other continents.
And so we reach all the people in this world.
Just sitting here.
And then you can start further
with the animals in this world, the fish.
I’m not talking about types of animals.
I’m talking about helping each individual animal.
Each one is looking at you. Each one is waiting.
Each one is afraid.
Each one is getting your personal guarantee.
“I’m handling this. I’ll take care of this.”
Just imagine going through each creature, the tiny creatures  at the bottom of the sea.
Tiny creatures in your blood.
Get to know each of them.
Talk to them.
And when you're done with all the life in this world,
we'll go to the next world.
I don't know where the next world is.
I don't know, maybe it's Alpha Centauri?
Maybe it's as far away as many light years.
Go there and start doing the same meditation
for all the people on that world.
And in this way, we encompass every world
in the entire universe.
And the karma of meeting one by one
with each of the seven billion human beings,
and with trillions of other beings on one planet,
and then encompassing as many planets as there are. Countless planets.
Embracing every being out there,
that's bodhichitta.
That's the direct experience of bodhichitta.
So please, for this class,
if you can just feel it.
You shouldn't worry about yourself.
You shouldn't worry about your family.
You really shouldn't worry about your country.
And you shouldn't worry about the world being engulfed by a virus. It's all such small things!
By the way, we'll take care of it.  about them.
We are working on a big project.
We are making a commitment to help the entire universe.
Countless billions of beings.
Countless billions of animals and other beings.
And we have this opportunity. You have this opportunity. I pray that you achieve this in this life.
I pray that you discover this in this life.
Your mind is already capable of touching every single sentient being and promising them that you will take care of them.
So the purpose of this lam-rim,
the purpose of this retreat,
is something like a journey to the middle of the sun.
Think of every single sentient being.
Countless sentient beings in the universe without boundaries.
Meet them one by one.
Make the promise one by one.
This is what happens
during the first direct experience of bodhichitta.
It actually happens.
This is what it is like.
If you keep imagining it,
it will help it happen.
Really!
So it is up to you if you want it to come.
If you really want to be a real bodhisattva,
then practice.
Practice this visualization once or twice.  per day.
Just whenever you have a few minutes. Just imagine.
In your imagination, okay?
And that will help it happen.
And you will attain bodhichitta.
Then something like a virus, for that kind of bodhisattva, a virus is not a very important thing.
It's a very, very small thing.
Making money. Making a
living. Feeding
your family.
Finding an apartment.
These are incredibly tiny things. There's nothing
there.
Your mind is like--
your heart is like the middle of the sun.
And a few more, I don't know, a few cookies or a few Cokes in the middle of the sun, it doesn't matter.
It's not that important.
Go for the big thing!
Everything else becomes small.
And everything else becomes convenient. Easy.
That's bodhichitta.
Okay!
See you in the next class.
Class 10.